让我们开始吧，欢迎回到这是凝聚态的第十一讲
let's get going welcome back this is the
eleventh lecture of the condensed matter
我们上次学习互惠空间的课程
course where we left off last time we
were studying reciprocal space
互惠的空间，我们来到这种理解
reciprocal space and we came to this
understanding that the reciprocal
晶格是直接晶格的傅立叶变换，也是我们产生晶格的原因
lattice is somehow the Fourier transform
of the direct lattice and the reason we
想研究互惠空间是因为它将使我们的生活
want to study reciprocal space is
because it's going to make our life
当我们学习波浪时比较容易，所以这是一件相当重要的事情
easier when we come to studying waves so
it's a rather important thing to to
很好理解，有时也很难理解傅立叶变换
understand well and sometimes it's hard
to understand Fourier transform as well
因为它们不是我们在日常生活中考虑的东西，而是
because they're not something that we
think about in everyday life it's a
有点复杂，所以事实证明，有一种更好的几何方法
little bit complicated so it turns out
that there's a much nicer geometric way
了解很多相互的空间，这是我们将要讨论的
to understand a lot of reciprocal space
which is what we're going to discuss
今天，我像往常一样需要一些定义，让我们从一个简单的开始
today so I need some definitions as
usual let's start with a simple
定义一个晶格平面等于一个包含三个三个平面
definition a lattice plane equals a
plane containing containing three three
非共线非共线线性，因此线性，因此
non collinear non collinear linear and
therefore linear and therefore an
无限数量，因此晶格点无限
infinite number and therefore infinity
of lattice points
好吧，所以晶格平面是包含三个非共线和
okay so a lattice plane is a plane
containing three non collinear and
因此，无数个晶格点，所以这是一些
therefore an infinite number of lattice
points so here's some pictures of
晶格平面这里我们在左边，我们有一个BCC晶格，还有一个平面
lattice planes here we on the Left we
have a BCC lattice there's a plane
穿过三个点，因此如果您继续到无穷远，它将
cutting through three points therefore
if you continued out to infinity it will
切掉无穷多个点，它们是晶格平面上的
cut through an infinity number of points
that's the lattice plane there's on the
右边是这个简单的立方格子，有一个平面可以切成三个
right is this simple cubic lattice
there's a plane that cuts through three
晶格点，如果您继续到无穷大，它将切入无限
lattice points if you continue out to
infinity it cuts through an infinite
晶格点数另一个定义是晶格平面族
number of lattice points another
definition a family of lattice planes of
格子飞机妈妈格子飞机婴儿格子飞机现在我在开玩笑那不是
lattice planes mama lattice plane baby
lattice plane now I'm joking that's not
在这个班上没有人笑过的是家庭最后一架飞机等于
what uh no one ever laughs in this class
it is families last planes equals an
无限无限等距等距等距格
infinite infinite infinite and finite
set equally spaced equal spaced lattice
包括所有晶格点和所有平面点的平面
planes such that such that all lattice
points all flat points are included are
包括在一架飞机中的飞机让我知道我的写作是否开始
included in one of the planes in planes
let me know if my writing starts getting
太杂乱而无法阅读，所以这里有一个简单的立方晶格和几个
to be too messy to read so here's a
simple cubic lattice and a couple of
晶格平面族这些剪切的晶格平面中的每一个
families of lattice planes each one of
these the lattice planes that cut
通过无数个晶格点，它们之间的间距相等，
through an infinite number of lattice
points and they're equally spaced and
当包含所有元素时，它们包括晶格中的每个点
they include every single point in the
lattice when taken all together this is
一个BCC晶格，并且BCC晶格切割有一系列晶格计划
a BCC lattice and there's a family of
lattice plans for the BCC lattice cuts
通过BCC晶格中的所有晶格点，但这不是一个族
through all the lattice points in the
BCC lattice this however is not a family
BCC晶格的晶格平面，即使它们的晶格平面是什么
of lattice planes for the BCC lattice
even though their lattice planes what's
绘制它们等距，但它们不包括
drawn they are equally spaced but they
do not include
他们在常规比赛中错过了这些家伙的格子点
the lattice point they miss these guys
here in the middle of the conventional
因此，它不是晶格平面族，所以连接
unit cell therefore it is not a family
of lattice planes okay so the connection
到相互的晶格平面晶格平面族
to the reciprocal lattice plane a family
of lattice planes family of lattice
平面垂直于倒数晶格矢量，我称之为G
planes is perpendicular to a reciprocal
lattice vector back which I'll call G
进一步和距离间距
and further and the distance the spacing
相邻平面之间的距离D等于PI
between between neighbor planes between
neighbor planes planes is D equals to PI
超过绝对G min，其中恶魔等于的最短沉淀晶格矢量
over absolute G min where demon a demon
equals shortest precip lattice vector at
lat BEC朝向G方向
lat
BEC in direction in direction of G okay
每当我们有一个晶格平面族时，这就是一个重要的陈述
this is an important statement every
time we have a family of lattice planes
与该晶格平面族正交，存在互易晶格
orthogonal to this family of lattice
planes there is a reciprocal lattice
向量，如果您想知道晶格平面之间的间距
vector and if you want to know the
spacing between the lattice planes in
晶格平面族，您会发现最短的倒易晶格矢量
the family of lattice planes you find
the shortest reciprocal lattice vector
在那个方向上指向PI超过那个最短的绝对值
pointing in that direction to PI over
the absolute value of that shortest
倒数晶格向量为您提供平面之间的间距
reciprocal lattice vector gives you the
spacing between planes okay this is a
我们尚未证明的重要声明，实际上证明这一声明很有用
big statement we haven't shown it it's
useful to actually prove this statement
因为实际上在证明中，我们有很多重要的几何
because actually in the proof there's a
lot of important geometry that we're
一会儿需要，所以让我们通过证明
going to need in coming up in a moment
so let's go through the proof that this
是真的，所以首先，这只是一个证明
is true so first of all so this is just
a proof
首先，您可能还记得一些几何图形
by geometry a little bit of geometry
that you probably remember first of all
它定义了我们的向量G G点的平面拾取点x等于常数C
it's define a plane pick of our vector G
G dot points x equals a constant C
定义一个平面，该平面找到点X垂直的点的平面
defines a plane it finds a plane of
points of points points X perpendicular
垂直于G的G，好的，实际上我可以在此处绘制
to G perpendicular to G where okay let
me actually draw this over here so
这是零点这是向量G这是垂直于G的平面
here's the point zero here's the vector
G here's the plane perpendicular to G
当调用X时，这是点X的平面和距零的距离
which when calling X this is the plane
of points X and the distance from zero
到飞机X的距离叫X min ya，其中X min最小
to the plane X let's call that distance
X min ya where X min the minimum
到平面的距离等于C超过绝对G，好吗？
distance to the plane equals C over
absolute G okay does that geometry look
之前看起来很熟悉，看起来还不错，所以这里的X分钟是C
familiar from before it does it look
reasonable yeah so the X min here is C
如果我们用GX定义平面等于C，那么绝对G就可以了
over absolute G if we're defining the
plane by GX equals equals C okay so
这就是您要如何定义一个平面现在我们要定义一组
that's how are you going to define a
plane now we're going to define a set of
我们由每个I GE x定义的平面的平面集合等于1，所以为什么
planes set of planes of planes we define
by each of the I GE x equals 1 so why
是否将平面集合定义为IG点x等于1的e相同
does that define the set of planes well
e to the I G dot x equals 1 is the same
说GX等于2 pi M，其中m是整数M，有一个元素
thing as saying GX equals 2 pi M where m
is an integer M there's an element of
正确的整数，所以这意味着我们有一堆最小的平面
integers right so so that means we have
a whole bunch of planes whose minimum
距原点的距离为2 pi M，因此X min等于绝对G上的2 pi M
distance to the origin is given by 2 pi
M so X min equals 2 pi M over absolute G
因此，这些平面之间的空间平面D之间的间距为2 PI
so space in between these planes spacing
between planes planes D is 2 PI over
绝对G好吧，实际上我对它的了解比我能画的要好
absolute G okay let's actually I have a
better picture of that than I can draw
所以我们感兴趣的几何形状是e等于IG x等于1，它定义了一组
so the geometry we're interested in is e
to the IG x equals 1 it defines a set of
平行平面中的一个将是GX等于
parallel planes
one of the planes will be GX equals to
PI M另一个平面将是x处的G等于PI M加第一个平面的距离1
PI M another plane will be G at x equals
to PI M plus 1 the distance of the first
平面在绝对G上为2 pi M，第二个距离为第二pi
plane is 2 pi M over absolute G the
second distance the second plane is 2 pi
并在绝对G上加1，因此两者之间的距离在G上为2 pi
and plus 1 over absolute G so the
distance between the two is 2 pi over G
几何看起来还不错吗，是的，好吧，所以现在回想一下，如果G
is that geometry look pretty good yeah
ok good alright so now recall that if G
是倒数晶格向量，所以G是倒数向量，我们再往后
is a reciprocal lattice vector so G is
reciprocal vector we sip flat back then
对于所有间接格，对于所有的间接格，e到i gr等于1
e to the i gr equals 1 for all for all
our indirect lattice and indirect that's
互易晶格的定义，这样告诉我们的是
a definition of the reciprocal lattice
so that what that tells us is that every
晶格点将包含在这组平面中，因为
lattice point is going to be included
inside this set of planes okay because
如果g是倒数晶格，则任何R都必须满足EBI g点r等于1
any R will have to satisfy EBI g dot r
equals 1 if g is reciprocal lattice
向量，所以我们在直接晶格中的所有晶格点都将是
vector so all of our lattice points in
the direct lattice are going to be
包括在我们刚刚定义的这套飞机中，但这并不意味着
included in this set of planes that we
just defined however it does not mean
每个飞机都切过晶格点好吧，为什么不好，这是这里的
that every plane cuts through lattice
points okay why not okay here's a here's
图片说明，这里我们有一组由一些倒数定义的平面
a picture to explain that here we have a
set of planes defined by some reciprocal
我将恰好称为G min的晶格矢量，在这里我们有一组平面
lattice vector which I'll happen to call
G min and here we have a set of planes
由两倍的倒数晶格矢量定义
devided defined by twice that reciprocal
lattice vector the spacing between the
晶格平面大一半，因为在G上间距始终为2 pi
lattice planes is half as big because
the spacing is always 2 pi over G you'll
请注意，在第二张图片中，我们有一个由此定义的平面
notice it in the second picture we have
a plane which is defined by this
不与任何晶格点相交的倒数晶格矢量G
reciprocal lattice vector G which
doesn't intersect any lattice points
该法所保证的是，所有直接晶格点必须是
what were guaranteed by this law is that
all direct lattice points must be
包括在一架飞机中，但不能保证每个飞机都必须
included in one of the planes but were
not guaranteed that every plane has to
穿过晶格点好吧，所以如果我们想得到一组平面
cut through a lattice point okay so if
we want to get a set of planes in which
每个飞机上的每个人都穿过我们必须选择的晶格点
everyone every plane cuts through
lattice points we have to choose so to
得到晶格平面的晶格族，并成为晶格平面
get family of lattice planes of lattice
planes and to be a lattice plane it has
必须穿过一个晶格点，所以如果我们要设置一组平面
to has to cut through a lattice point so
if we want to set of planes where every
平面切过一个晶格点，我们必须选择必须选择最短的gmm
plane cuts through a lattice point we
must choose must choose gmm the shortest
给定方向上的倒数晶格矢量（如果不是最小值）
reciprocal lattice vector in that given
direction if it was not the minimum
在该方向上的倒数晶格矢量，您可以将其缩小
reciprocal lattice vector in that
direction you could make it smaller cut
例如，将其减半，得到的飞机平面更少，但所有
it in half for example and get something
which has fewer planes and yet all of
晶格点仍应包括在内，因此您应尽量减少
the lattice points should still be
included so you should take the minimum
倒数晶格矢量，以便获得足够的平面
reciprocal lattice vector so that you
get enough planes
确保您所有的晶格点都在直接晶格中
there's guaranteed that all all your
lattice points in the direct lattice
将被包括在那些飞机上，但是您没有得到任何额外的好处，好吧
will be included in those planes but you
don't get any extra okay good all right
这就是那个相当重要的定理的证明，现在是
so that's the the proof of that of that
rather important theorem now it's it's
实际提出一些描述这些相互关系的方法很有用
useful to actually come up with some
some way to describe these reciprocal
晶格平面是这些晶格平面族或这些倒数
lattice planes are these these family of
lattice planes or these reciprocal
格向量，这是一种符号，我们将非常使用
lattice vectors and this is a type of
notation that we will use very
通常被称为米勒指数
frequently known as Miller indices for
用于描述描述飞机系列的飞机
describing for describing describe
families of planes planes planes
或收件人米勒索引中可观空间向量中的向量是
or vectors in respectable space vectors
in recipient Miller index is that you
用圆括号HK L表示实际上也许我会先
write in parentheses HK L to mean
actually maybe maybe I'll before I do
好吧，我们描述了互易空间中平面或向量的族
that alright we describe families of
planes or vectors in reciprocal space in
XB sub I的参考向量项的术语这些B sub I是
terms of terms of reference vectors
reference of X B sub I these B sub I is
非常重要的是它们可能是原始的原始倒易晶格矢量或
very important they may be primitive
primitive reciprocal lattice vectors or
他们可能通常不是我们要做的是我们写的是我开始写的
they may not be generally what we do is
we write was I starting to write a
括号中的第二行HK L表示H乘b1加K乘b2加L乘b3
second go HK L in parentheses to mean H
times b1 plus K times b2 plus L times b3
这个符号看起来有点熟悉，我们可以将其与
and this notation should look a little
bit familiar we can compare it to the
我们在现实空间中使用的符号间接空间直接空间中我们使用的符号u
notation we use in real space indirect
space direct space we use the notation u
v W表示u乘以1加V乘以2加W乘以3，所以重要的是
v W to mean u times a 1 plus V times a 2
plus W times a 3 so the important thing
要带走的是，如果我们在此处使用弯曲的括号，则表示
to take away here is that if we use
curved parentheses here we mean
倒数空间，如果我们使用方括号，是指直接空间，所以不要
reciprocal space if we use square
brackets we mean direct space so don't
现在在这两种情况下将它们彼此混淆，我们可能或可能不是故意的
confuse those with each other now in
both cases we may or may not mean these
这些B的帮助是原始的，这很重要，因为很多
aids of these B's to be primitive okay
that's very important because a lot of
考试中出现的问题恰好参考了这种细微之处
the questions that come up on exams
exactly reference this subtlety that
有时您使用原始晶格事实倒数晶格矢量
sometimes you work with primitive
lattice fact reciprocal lattice vectors
或原始晶格向量，有时您不为什么不使用
or primitive lattice vectors and
sometimes you don't why don't use
有时是因为有时原始格向量或原始
sometimes because sometimes the
primitive lattice vectors or primitive
倒数晶格向量是丑角，如果您选择使用
reciprocal lattice vectors are ugly
angles and if you choose to use a
可以使用常规单位单元而不是原始单位单元
conventional unit cell rather than
primitive unit cell you can use
正交向量而不是使用怪异角度的东西，所以如果可以的话
orthogonal vectors rather than using
things that weird angles so if you can
使用正交通常可以做到，即使这意味着您没有使用
use orthogonal you usually
do even if it means you're not using
原始晶格矢量还可以，所以在这里要小心
primitive lattice vectors okay
so let's be be careful here being
小心小心我们的定义，规则就像
careful being careful about our
definitions the rules kind of go like
首先选择直接实空间返回直接空间矢量
this first choose direct real space back
there's direct space vectors direct
空间向量是一个子I，可能是这些东西，也可能不是
space vectors a sub I that's going to be
these things which may or may not be
我什至会写成原始的，可能不是PL v z-- p LVS
primitive I'll even write that down may
or may not may not be PL v z-- p LVS now
对我们来说，您会记得我们有一条规则，那就是我们不会负责任
for us you'll remember we had this rule
that we're not going to be responsible
对于三维的晶格，其中轴不是正交的
for lattices in three dimensions where
the axes are not orthogonal okay for us
对于我们在3D中，我们总是选择选择正交正交A
for us in 3d we always choose choose
orthogonal orthogonal A's okay
有时在2D中，他们会问一个问题：它们不是正交的，但在3D中
sometimes in 2d they'll ask a question
where they're not orthogonal but in 3d
我们总是选择选择正交A表示简单立方
we always choose choose orthogonal A's
that means for simple cubic simple cubic
三次，这些可以是原始格向量tlv，但对于FCC FCC和
cubic these can be these are primitive
lattice vectors tlvs but for FCC FCC and
BCC不是PL v，但它们具有正交的优势
BCC these are not not PL v's but they
have the advantage of being orthogonal
因此，它们使您的生活变得更加轻松，因为使用起来更加轻松
so they make your life a lot easier
because it's a lot easier to work with
正交的东西比不正交的东西还好
things that are orthogonal than things
that are not orthogonal okay so given
我们已经定义了这些A，然后构造了B，因此可以这样称呼为
that we've defined these A's we then
construct B's so can so call that to
构造B的
construct construct B's
bi bi AJ等于2 pi Delta IJ，我们在如果且仅当
bi bi AJ equals 2 pi Delta IJ and we've
seen this equation before if if and only
如果是我们的PL B，那么蜜蜂将是倒数，我们的倒数是这些
if is our pl B's then bees will be
reciprocal our reciprocal repeal these
如果lat P lbs原语，我们在Reese是典型的吗
are we
typical at Reese if lat P lbs primitive
格点向量对我们来说再好一次，因为我们已经在3d中使用3d
lattice vectors okay again for us for us
since we are already using in 3d in 3d
由于我们一直在3D中使用正交轴，因此总是
since we are always using orthogonal
axes in 3d it will always turn out to be
BI的绝对值等于PI超过PI的绝对值的情况
the case that the absolute value of BI
equals to PI over the absolute value of
AI因为x是正交轴正交好所以使生活很多
比较容易，所以一般来说，当我们写下G等于HK L时，我们的意思是
easier so generally when we write down G
equals HK L we mean where is it this
HB 1 + K ma已经是我们的意思了HB 1 + KB 2 + LB
thing over here HB 1 plus K ma already
again we mean H B 1 plus K B 2 plus L B
3以这种方式构造的蜜蜂，但总是G定义了一组
3 where the bees have been constructed
in this way but always G defines a set
平面定义了一组平面，一组平面通过e到达IG x
of planes defines a set of planes a set
of planes planes via e to the IG x
等于1 e到I GE x等于1，所以您可以始终定义一组平面
equals 1 e to the I GE x equals 1 so you
can always define a set of planes from
通过e到IG x的任何向量G等于1，并且这些平面的间距
any vector G via e to the IG x equals 1
and the spacing of these planes spacing
是d HK l等于绝对G的2pi还是我假设是在正交轴上
is d HK l equals 2pi over absolute G or
I guess in assuming orthogonal axes
假设正交蜜蜂正交A的正交正交10蜜蜂正交
assume orthogonal bees orthogonal A's
orthogonals a 10 bees orthogonal
正交的
orthogonal
那么我们可以写成2 pi超过H平方的绝对值
then we have we can write that as 2 pi
over absolute value of H squared
绝对b1平方加K平方绝对b2平方加
absolute b1 squared
plus K squared absolute b2 squared plus
l平方恰好是3平方，对于立方晶格，对于立方，对于立方
l squared happens to be 3 squared ok and
for cubic lattice for cubic for cubic
其中a 1 2和a 3的长度相同且彼此正交
where a 1 a 2 and a 3 are the same
length and orthogonal to each other
因此B 1 B 2 B 3的长度相同且彼此正交
therefore B 1 B 2 B 3 are the same
length and are orthogonal to each other
间距D HKL是图元的长度，是常规长度
the spacing D HKL is a the length of the
primitive the length of the conventional
H平方加K平方加l平方的间接空间中的晶胞
unit cell in indirect space over H
squared plus K squared plus l squared
好吧，也许我会再注意一次，如果A是PL而不是A是PL B
okay and maybe I'll note this one more
time if the A's are PL vs A's are PL B's
然后蜜蜂是PL V，然后是B的PL V，将其写在B的PL V之上，
then the bees are PL V's then B's PL V's
to write that above B's PL V's and that
表示H KL是倒数晶格向量，我们向后倾斜，但不是
means that H KL is a reciprocal lattice
vector we sip lat back but it's not
总是这样，如果A不是PL V的开头
always the case
if the A's are not PL V's to start with
好吧，假设某人递给您一套飞机，并要求您
ok all right so supposing someone hands
you a set of planes and asked you for
听起来很难找到米勒指数，但实际上
the Miller indices that sounds like it
might be hard to figure out but in fact
有一种简单的方法可以从几何上找出米勒指数
there's an easy way to figure out
geometrically what the Miller indices
是针对一组平面的，这称为拦截方法
are for a set of planes and this is
known as the method of intercept method
的截距有点像这样，所以假设我们有这样的
of intercepts goes kind of like kind of
like this so suppose we have so here's
三个轴x轴，y轴和z轴让我们假设是正交的，因此
three axes x-axis the y-axis and the
z-axis let's assume orthorhombic so the
基本晶格矢量和三个方向不一定相同
primitive lattice vectors and the three
directions aren't necessarily the same
所以称这为二和二为二，这将是我猜为1 2 A 1 3 a 1
so call this a two and two a two and
this one will be I guess a 1 2 A 1 3 a 1
4 a 1在这里，然后是三到三和三a
4 a 1 here
then a three to a three and three a
三个假设我们要坐飞机
three
so suppose that we have a plane going
穿过原点，想象一下这里有一架飞机穿过原点
through the origin so imagine there's a
plane cutting through the origin here
然后像这样切开轴，所以您将前两个
and then also cuts through the axes like
this okay so you take the first two
其中一个平行平面切成与该平面平行的原点
parallel planes one of them cuts to the
origin it's parallel to this plane which
像这样切开轴，规则是HKL也许我会这样写
cuts through the axes like this the rule
is that HKL maybe I'll write it this way
H是2 K是2 L，因为其比例与x截距上的1相同
H is 2 K is 2 L as a proportionality is
the same as a 1 over the x intercept is
y截距上的2 a 2是Z截距上的2 a 3，所以在此图片中
2 a 2 over the y intercept is 2 a 3 over
the Z intercept so in this picture here
这将是1超过x截距是1超过4 a 2是超过y截距
this would be a 1 over the x intercept
is 1 over 4 a 2 is over the y intercept
是2上的1，Z截距上的3是3的1，所以它应该具有相同的
is 1 over 2 and a 3 over the Z intercept
is 1 over 3 so it should have the same
如果我们乘以最小公倍数和最小公倍数
ratios as this if we multiply by the
least common multiple least common
倍数，我们得到3逗号6逗号4作为Miller指数将是适当的
multiple we get 3 comma 6 comma 4 as
Miller indices that would be appropriate
对于这个平面，通常您将其写为3 6 4，而在不带任何逗号的情况下
for this this plane and generally you
write it as 3 6 4 without any commas at
至少只要不混淆应该放在哪里的逗号
least as long as there's no confusion as
to where you should put the commas if
如果您超过10，则必须指出逗号在哪里，否则不是
you go over 10 then you have to indicate
where the commas are otherwise it's not
清楚现在如果在这里和这以及我们在这里所说的3 6 4意味着什么
clear where it would be all right now if
and this and what we mean by 3 6 4 here
3 6 4是3 B 1加上6 B 2加上4 B 3，这就是我们所说的
is that 3 6 4 is 3 B 1 plus 6 B 2 plus 4
B 3 and that's what we mean by the
米勒指数和那套米勒指数是倒数
Miller indices and that that set of
Miller indices is gives a reciprocal
与此平面垂直的晶格矢量在某些情况下
lattice vector which is normal to this
to this plane there's a some cases which
如果一个平面不与访问相交，则要复杂一些
are a little more complicated if a plane
if a plane does not intersect an access
平面不相交访问不相交
plane does not not intersect an access
not intersect
与轴相交，则得到的密勒指数为零，得到密勒指数
intersect an axis then you get a miller
index of zero you get Miller index index
等于零，让我们看看是否可以解释那是什么
equals zero let's see if we can explain
what that is
所以这里又是三个轴，这是一个轴，这里可能是2
so here again three axes this is the a
one axis out here maybe this will be a 2
这将是2 a 2，也许在这里我们有383，假设我们有一个轴
this will be 2 a 2 and maybe here we
have 383 and suppose we have an axis
轴总是切一个平面，总是切过0，然后再切下一个
axis always cut an a plane always
cutting through 0 and then the next
平面在这里切割，但它平行于x轴的a 1轴，因此从不
plane cuts here but it's parallel to the
a 1 axis here to the x axis so it never
拦截它，那么我们如何处理Miller指数呢？我们说H为2 K为2
intercepts it so what do we do with the
Miller indices well we say H is 2 K is 2
L也好，所以第一个问题是，如果
L as well okay so the first question is
where do we intercept the x-axis well if
它完全不拦截x轴，您可以说这真的像
it doesn't intercept the x-axis at all
you can say that it's really like
与x轴在无穷大处相交，因此我们在无穷大处写入1，然后在K
intersecting the x-axis at infinity so
we write 1 over infinity here and then K
好吧，我们在2处的y轴与2相交，而在3处的z轴与相交
well we intersect the y-axis at 2 so 1
over 2 and we intersect the z-axis at 3
因此，我们将1覆盖3并乘以最小公倍数，得到1覆盖
so we write 1 over 3 and multiply by the
least common multiple and we get 1 over
无穷大0 3 3 2所以这里的米勒指数是0 3 2好的，让我展示
infinity 0 3 3 2 so the Miller indices
here would be 0 3 2 okay so let me show
您的几个示例这是一组1 0 0的Miller索引
you a couple examples of this here's a
set of Miller indices that are 1 0 0
因为它在1处与X相交，而与Z或Y不相交，所以这里是1 1 2
because it intersects X at 1 and doesn't
intersect Z or Y here's one that's 1 1 2
因为它与1处的1 y处的X和1处的Z相交，所以1/2的倒数是2
because it intersects X at 1 y at 1 and
Z at 1/2 the reciprocal of 1/2 is 2 so
是1 1 2所以你可以有一个情况
it's 1 1 2 so you can have a situation
可以具有小于0的米勒指数
can have can have Miller index less than
0 index
负
negative
像1-1 0，通常写成1 1，而在0处有一个横线
like 1-1 0 which you typically write as
1 1 with a bar over at 0 okay so the bar
条形表示否定表示否定，这只是常规的表示法
bar means negative means negative that's
just the notation that's conventionally
现在可以使用了，所以对于我们不协调的人来说，这是一个很大的道歉
used now ok so here is a great big
apology for the uncoordinated of our
社区，所以取决于您所说的方式来自海洋的哪一边
community so depending on what side of
the ocean you come from the way you say
如果您来自美国，那声音大不一样，您说1 1巴
this out loud is different if you're
from the United States you say 1 1 bar
如果您来自英国，则为0，您说1 bar 1 0我不知道为什么会这样
is 0 if you're from England you say 1
bar 1 0 I don't know why it makes things
令人难以置信的是，它写的时候完全不清楚
incredibly confusing when it's written
it's totally unambiguous the bar on top
表示负面，但当您大声说出来时，这完全令人困惑，没有人
means negative but when you say it out
loud it's totally confusing and no one
知道你的意思，所以我建议先写下来然后
knows what you what you mean so I
recommend just writing it down and then
每个人都知道你在说什么好吧，让我给你看一个例子，
everyone knows what you're talking about
ok let me show you an example where we
米勒指数为负，所以这架飞机实际上可能并非如此
have a negative Miller index so this
plane here actually maybe it's not so
清楚，但应该是您应该能够
clear but but it's supposed to you
supposed to sort of be able to
用你的眼睛往下推，看到这架飞机有点像
extrapolate down with your with your
eyes and see that this plane is sort of
从此处开始然后向下移动，并且与z轴相交为负1/2，因此
starts up here and goes down and would
intersect the z-axis at minus 1/2 and so
它的截距是1 1减去1/2，所以它是Miller指数或1 1 2与
it's intercepts are 1 1 minus 1/2 so
it's Miller indices or 1 1 2 with the
否定为负2好的，所以这里有一堆不同的Miller指数
bar over it negative 2 ok so here's a
whole bunch of different Miller indices
对于一堆不同的飞机，他是0 0 1 1 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 0 1依此类推
for bunches of different planes he's 0 0
1 1 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 so forth and so on
您会发现他们实际上实际上是某种家庭成员，所以如果
and you see that they actually they
actually kind of come in families so if
您会在第一行的第一行看到家庭，您会看到0
you look at the family across the top
row across the top row you'll see the 0
0 1和1 0 0它们看起来相似，而0 1 0看起来相似，如果
0 1 and 1 0 0 they kind of look similar
and 0 1 0 looks kind of similar and if
您以为实际上有一个样品，您知道这是一个简单的立方晶格，
you imagined actually having a sample
you know it's a simple cubic lattice and
您拿起简单的立方晶格，然后从一侧对其进行了观察1 0 0
you picked up the simple cubic lattice
and you looked at it from one side 1 0 0
看起来就像0 1 0，具体取决于您是否将其拿起并打开
would look exactly like 0 1 0 depending
on if you picked it up and turn it
侧面完全一样，只是取决于您拿起的那一侧，
sideways it's exactly the same it just
depends on which side you picked up and
先看类似的1 0 1或1 1 0
looked at first
similarly with 1 0 1 or 1 1 0 if you
拿起它，你侧眼看着它会
picked it up and you looked at it
sideways it would
飞机和那些家庭之间的距离完全一样
exactly the same okay the spacing
between planes and those families would
与通过设备斜切的方式完全相同
be exactly the same the way it cuts
diagonally through the through the unit
单元格看起来一样，只是选择哪种方式很重要
cell would look the same
it just matters which way you picked it
首先，所以我们有一个等效的符号
up in the first place
so we have a notation for equivalent
米勒指数集等同于我们的米勒指数集
sets of Miller indices equivalent sets
of Miller indices indices which we
请注意，我们有大括号，像那样可怕的大括号
notate we have curly brackets okay
that's terrible curly bracket like that
HKL表示等值集等效于HDL和常规括号
HKL which means equivalent sets equiv
sets of HDL and regular parentheses
方括号，例如，在此图片中，大括号1 0 0表示1 0 0或
brackets so for example in this picture
curly brackets 1 0 0 would mean 1 0 0 or
0 1 0或0 0 1或1 bar 0 0或0 1 bar 0或0 0 1 bar巧合
0 1 0 or 0 0 1 or 1 bar 0 0 or 0 1 bar 0
or 0 0 1 bar on coincidentally you know
这些平面看起来像立方体的表面，您可以拾取
these planes look like the surface of a
cube and you can pick up the surface of
一个多维数据集，并以6种不同的方式查看它，从所有角度来看，它看起来都是等效的
a cube and look at it 6 different ways
and it would look equivalent from all
这六个不同的角度，我们也有称为HK L的多重性
those six different angles we also have
what's known as the multiplicity of HK L
该数字等于括号HK L中括号HK L的数量，因此
which is the number equals the number of
parentheses HK L in bracket HK L so in
在这种情况下，我们将具有1 0 0的多重性是6，因为它包括所有这些
this case we would have multiplicity of
1 0 0 is 6 because it includes all those
我写下了六组不同的米勒指数，所以对于第一个
six different sets of Miller indices
that I wrote down okay so for the first
一天的糖果吧1 2 3的多重性是多少
candy bar of the day what is the
multiplicity of 1 2 3 no
现在是谁说某事48是的，这个谁说48
now who is it someone said something
48 yeah yeah this who said that 48 this
一个人的你很好，我不能把它扔得那么远
one's yours very good I can't throw it
that far
48答案是48，所以让我们看看为什么它的多重性是48
48 the answer is 48 so let's see why the
multiplicity of this is 48
首先，两个和三个可以任意顺序排列，所以这是六个事实，或者是
first of all one two and three can be in
any order so that's six fact or that's
三个阶乘给您6 1 2 3 1 3 2 2 3 1 2 1 3 3 1 2 3 2 1 6可能的方式
three factorial gives you 6 1 2 3 1 3 2
2 3 1 2 1 3 3 1 2 3 2 1 6 possible ways
订购它们，但是除此之外，这些数字中的任何一个都可以有一个小节
of ordering them but then in addition
any one of those numbers can have a bar
是否在它上面所以这有2种可能性这有2种可能性
over it or not so this one has 2
possibilities this has 2 possibilities
她有2种可能性，有8种可能性，所以是8乘以6
this she has 2 possibilities that makes
8 possibilities so it's 8 times 6 gives
你48好吧，所以1 2 3的多重性等于48，这很有趣
you 48 okay so multiplicity of 1 2 3
equals 48 which is kind of interesting
这意味着您是否拥有与1 2 3相关的晶格平面族
it means if you have the family of
lattice planes associated with the 1 2 3
您可以从米勒索引中选取一个简单的立方晶格，然后从48
Miller indices you can pick up a simple
cubic lattice and look at it from 48
方向不同，且晶格面的间距完全相同
different directions and have lattice
planes with exactly the same spacings
看着你好吧，但那是真的
looking at you okay
sort of surprising but but that's true
好吧，为什么现在我们为什么如此关心这些晶格平面呢？
ok so now why is it we care so much
about these these lattice planes besides
他们会告诉我们很多关于互惠空间的事实，而我们
the fact that they're going to tell us a
lot about reciprocal space and we're
对波浪和波浪感兴趣，您知道互易空间是波浪的语言
interested in waves and waves you know
reciprocal space is a language of waves
这是我们可能对这些晶格家族感兴趣的原因之一
well the reason one reason we might be
interested in these families of lattice
互惠空间中的飞机是因为它们实际上告诉您很多有关
planes in reciprocal space is because
they actually tell you a lot about the
晶体的宏观结构，所有
macroscopic structure of the crystal
it's kind of interesting that all of
有关晶格平面和倒易晶格的信息，这就是全部
this information about lattice planes
and reciprocal lattices this was all
在人们甚至不知道有
worked out in the middle of the 1800s
before people even knew that there was
诸如原子之类的东西及其解决方法是因为人们知道
such thing as atoms and the way it was
worked out is because people knew that
矿物质好晶体，而矿物质破裂，相反，它们仅沿
minerals nice crystal and minerals broke
instead they fractured only along
某些轴，这使他们能够推断出所有这些信息，因此对于
certain axes and that enabled them to
deduce all of this information so for
例如，您会发现一个简单的立方格子或任何类型的立方
example with a simple cubic lattice
you'll discover or any type of cubic
点阵将打破材料将沿着简单打破
lattice that the lattice will will break
the material will break along simple
简单的Miller索引集，例如此处的1 0 0面或0 1 0面
simple sets of Miller indices so like
the 1 0 0 face here or the 0 1 0 face
这是材料最容易破裂的地方这是法律，不是
here is where the material will will
break most easily this is a law it's not
变硬了，但这是非常非常好的经验法则
a hardened
but it's a very very good rule of thumb
通过勇敢而著称的Brava是法律，是制定出所有晶格的那个人，
by brav a known as Brava is law the same
guy who worked out all the lattices and
它实际上告诉您，当您拿起立方晶体而破裂时
it actually tells you that when you when
you take a cubic crystal and you break
它只会得到1 0 0张脸，偶尔也会得到1 1 0张脸
it you get only the 1 0 0 faces
occasionally you'll get the 1 1 0 faces
甚至偶尔你会得到1 1 2，所以这是钠的照片
and even less occasionally you'll get 1
1 2 so here's a picture of sodium
氯化物是立方晶体，实际上是FCC晶体，会破裂
chloride which is a cubic crystal it's
it's actually FCC crystal and it breaks
几乎只沿1 0 0晶格平面，您可以看到这些
almost exclusively along the 1 0 0
lattice planes you can see that these
这些断裂完全是在90度石英上的，好吧，我们不研究石英
these breaks are entirely at 90 degrees
quartz okay we don't study quartz this
今年，这只是一张非常不错的图片，所以我把它放在那里，我们不学习
year this is just a very nice picture so
I put it in there and we don't study
今年，因为轴不正交，这是一个三角形
that this year because the axes are not
orthogonal to each other it's a trigonal
水晶，但轴非常清晰，面孔非常清晰，非常固定
crystal but the axes very clearly the
faces are very clearly at very fixed
彼此的角度由晶格平面的排列方式决定
angles to each other which are dictated
by how the lattice planes are arranged
好吧，我将再强调一次这个事实，因为它显示了
okay so I'm going to emphasize this one
fact one more time because it shows up
如此频繁地参加考试，因此如果沙皇POV能够处理
on exams so frequently so this is
important fact if a czar POVs then deal
如果并且只有一个阶段或POV，那么B或PL B的情况我想我已经记下了
if and only a phase or POVs then B's or
PL B's I think I've written this down
今天是三倍，那么这些是五月的收件人
three times today
then these are P of a may recipients
收到Racal VL B，我们饮这些
receive Racal VL B's we sip peel these
例如，对于简单三次就是如此，这意味着任何HKL为h b1加k
for example this is true for simple
cubic which means any HKL is h b1 plus k
b2这是HK L b3的定义，所以这些都是幽灵的补充
b2 this is the definition of HK L b3 so
any of these is a resupply the specter
我们喝lat BEC是因为原始晶格向量的整数和给您
we sip lat BEC because integer sums of
primitive lattice vectors give you an
格的元素，如果我们想要一个晶格平面族
element of the lattice if we want a
family of lattice planes a family of
我们应该拥有的经纬平面的晶格面应该最短
lattice planes of lat planes we should
have should hat should be shortest be
最短的
shortest
在最短的给定方向上，我们在给定的方向上flat平Veck
in a given direction shortest we sip
flat Veck in given direction so for
例如，如果我们考虑方向2 4 6是最短的倒数
example if we're considering the
direction 2 4 6 the shortest reciprocal
简单三次晶格中的最短倒易晶格矢量
lattice for the simple cubic lattice the
shortest reciprocal lattice vector in
那个方向是1 2 3所以u / /最大公约数所以如果你想
that direction is 1 2 3 so u / /
greatest common divisor so if you want
要描述一组晶格平面，您应该始终选择倒数
to describe a set of lattice planes you
should always choose the reciprocal
在给定方向上最短的晶格矢量，但是如果
lattice vector which is shortest in that
given direction however however if the
那么A不是PL V的，然后是，然后蜜蜂不是PL V的不收信
A's are not PL V's then and this is and
then the bees are not PL V's not recipie
Alize意味着不是我们所有的补给向量都是接收格
Alize which means that not all HK L our
resupply us vectors are recipt lattice
向量，这是大多数最优秀的考试问题的根源，好吧，让我
vectors and this is the source of most
most good exam problems okay so let me
告诉你确切的意思，所以我们称这张图片和晶格
show you exactly what we mean by this so
we call this picture and the lattice
我在这张图片中绘制的最后一架飞机的家族是1架飞机
planes that the family of last planes
I've drawn in this picture here is the 1
0 0族的晶格平面和G的最小倒数晶格矢量
0 0 family of lattice planes and and G
the minimum reciprocal lattice vector in
那个方向实际上是1 0 0这是简单的立方晶格，所以这是
that direction is in fact 1 0 0 this is
simple cubic lattice so this is
肯定是倒数晶格矢量中的晶格平面族现在有两次
definitely a family of lattice planes in
a reciprocal lattice vector now twice
到0 0是互易的晶格向量，但不是晶格族
that to 0 0 is a reciprocal lattice
vector but it's not a family of lattice
飞机，因为您有多余的飞机，您的飞机无法穿过
planes because you have extra planes you
have a plane that doesn't cut through
任何晶格都指向平面间距的一半，所以不是最后一个族
any lattice points half the spacing of
planes so it's not a family of last
平面，但是它是一个倒易的晶格矢量，现在让我们考虑一下
planes but it is a reciprocal lattice
vector now let's think about what
当我们转到带有BCC和FCC的BCC或FCC晶格时发生
happens when we go to either a BCC
or an FCC lattice with a BCC and FCC
格我们仍将使用相同的三个正交A
lattice we're still going to use the
same three orthogonal A's we're going to
选择使用常规单位晶格来定义我们的A
choose to use the conventional unit cell
to define our A's
就像我们对一个简单的立方晶格所做的一样，我们这样做并不是
just like we did with a simple cubic
lattice and we're doing this they're not
原始晶格因子，这是一个问题，但我们这样做是因为我们
primitive lattice factors and that's a
problem but we're doing it because we
想要保持一切正交，如果保持下去，生活会容易很多
want to keep everything orthogonal and
life is just a lot easier if you keep
一切都正交，所以这是一堆带有米勒指数的图片
everything orthogonal okay so here's a
picture with a bunch of Miller indices
还有一堆为简单立方晶格绘制的晶格平面，这里是1 0
and a bunch of lattice planes drawn for
the simple cubic lattice here's the 1 0
如果您添加了BCC案例中我之前绘制的0组晶格平面
0 set of lattice planes just like I drew
before now in the BCC case if you added
该单元格中心的另一个点
one more point in the center of that
unit cell in the center of that
常规的晶胞，它不会与1 0 0平面集合相交
conventional unit cell it would not be
intersected by the 1 0 0 set of planes
它与平面2 0 0集相交，所以2 0 0是一个正确的族
it is intersected by the 2 0 0 set of
planes so 2 0 0 is a correct family of
BCC的晶格面不是4 4简单立方确定是1 0 0甚至不是
lattice planes for BCC it is not 4 4
simple cubic ok is 1 0 0 isn't even a
BCC的互易晶格矢量，因为它并不与每个相交
reciprocal lattice vector for BCC
because it does not intersect every
晶格点好，那就是微妙之处，我们将回到
lattice point ok that's that's the
subtlety and we're going to come back to
对于BCC，这种微妙的选择一遍又一遍，您必须选择Miller指数
this subtlety over and over for a BCC
you have to choose Miller indices to
确保您的每个晶格点都包含在其中之一
make sure that every one of your lattice
points is included in one of those
飞机的FCC相同，这是有问题的原因是因为我们正在使用
planes the same for FCC and the reason
this is a problem is because we're using
不是我们正在使用的原始晶格矢量的晶格矢量a
lattice vectors a which are not the
primitive lattice vectors we're using
正交向量，因为正交使您的生活更容易相信或不相信
orthogonal vectors because orthogonal
makes your life easier believe it or not
如果我们考虑FCC晶格，并且考虑1 1 1，则与FCC相同
same with FCC if we consider the FCC
lattice and you consider the 1 1 1
这些平面在这里我们不会与这些晶格点相交
planes these planes here we would not
intersect some of these lattice points
这些将丢失，因此1 0 0不是FCC的倒数晶格矢量2 0 0
these would be missing so 1 0 0 is not a
reciprocal lattice vector for FCC 2 0 0
同样可以，虽然我们可以在这里看1 1 1所以1 1 1是个很好的集合
is okay similarly while we can look at 1
1 1 here so 1 1 1 is perfectly good set
一个简单立方的晶格平面族就不会是
a family of lattice planes for simple
cubic it would not be a family of
BCC的晶格平面，因为它会错过单元中心的点
lattice planes for BCC because it would
miss the point in the center of unit
单元，但实际上它是FCC的晶格平面族，因为它只是
cell but actually it is a family of
lattice planes for FCC because it just
碰巧可以捕捉到脸部中央的所有这些点
happens to catch all those points in the
center of the faces okay now later on
我们实际上将得出一个条件，该条件将告诉我们何时
we're actually going to derive a
condition which will tell us when we
有米勒指数，我们的家庭
have
Miller indices which our family of
特定晶格的晶格平面，但重要的是要了解并非每个晶格
lattice planes for a particular lattice
but it's important to realize not every
并非每套米勒指数的集合都会给你倒数的格子
set of not every set of Miller indices
will give you a reciprocal lattice
BCC和FCC晶格的向量或晶格平面族以及
vector or a family of lattice planes for
BCC and FCC lattice and the origin of
这个问题是我们没有使用原始格向量来描述
this problem is we're not using
primitive lattice vectors to describe
我们自己常规的我们正在使用常规单元电池的边缘
our conventional yourself we're using
the edges of the conventional unit cell
好的，很明显，我已经警告过您足够多的好事了吗
okay is that clear
have I warned you enough all right good
好的，这就是我们要说的关于互惠空间的一切，现在我们
all right so that's everything we have
to say about reciprocal space and now we
可以进入互惠空间的某些应用，也许是最
can get on to some applications of
reciprocal space and perhaps the most
我们将要遇到的重要应用是散射实验
important application we're going to run
into is scattering experiments
散射实验，这将是本讲座其余部分的主题，
scattering experiments which will be the
subject of the rest of this lecture and
接下来的两堂课可能会讲很多，所以一般的散射实验
probably much of the next two lectures
so the general scattering experiment
从样本样本开始，您发送的是一些波向量为K的波
starts with a sample sample you send in
some wave with wave vector K some of it
经过无疤的波矢量k出现，其中一些出现在
goes through unscared comes out at wave
vector k and some of it comes out at
通过观察波向量k素产生的波向量k素
wave vector k prime by observing what
comes out at wave vector k prime you're
应该能够推断出样品中的成分现在很难高估
supposed to be able to deduce what is in
the sample now it's hard to overstate
您可能已经研究过这类实验的重要性
the importance of this type of
experiment you may have studied it in
其他课程，尤其是亚原子课程，但不是结束，不是
other courses especially subatomic but
it is not an over is not an
夸张地说，我们几乎所有关于微观的知识
overstatement to say that almost
everything we know about the microscopic
世界的一切，我们知道存在核的事实，我们
world everything the fact that we know
that there are nuclei the fact that we
知道原子的结构我们知道材料的结构
know the structure of atoms the fact
that we know the structure of materials
我们知道质子的结构这些事实都来自
the fact that we know the structure of
the proton all of these things come from
这类实验这种散射实验你知道我们成长了
this kind of experiment this type of
scattering experiment you know we grew
在一个甚至孩子都知道原子长什么样的世界里
up in a world where even kids know what
what atoms look like and they know what
DNA看起来像这个双链螺旋，他们知道水分子是什么
DNA looks like this double stranded
helix they know what water molecule
看起来他们甚至可能知道盐分选成什么氯钠
looks like they may even know what salt
looks like sodium chlorine is sorted
在我们知道并且理所当然的所有这些东西都来自做之前
before all of this stuff that we know
and we take for granted comes from doing
这种实验唯一的不同之处就是
this kind of experiment the only thing
that's different when we do this
实验与什么时候高能物理学家做这个实验是什么
experiment versus when the high energy
physicist doing this experiment is what
首先我们开始讨论，现在我们有兴趣看到原子
wave we put in to start with okay now
we're interested in seeing atoms and
原子的大小约为埃
atoms are on the scale of about an
angstrom at
事实证明，选择波长为
turns out to be a really good idea to
choose a way of whose wavelength is
您想要看到的东西的规模差不多，所以对我们来说，他们将成为
about the same scale of the thing you
want to see so for us they're gonna be a
几种选择之一是X射线电磁波，其长度尺度
couple of options one is x-rays
electromagnetic waves whose length scale
大约是一埃，这将使我们能够看到大小约为
is about an angstrom so that will enable
us to see things roughly of the size of
埃，但你知道我们生活在这个量子力学世界中，我们知道
an angstrom but you know we live in this
quantum mechanical world and we know
那波和粒子是同一件事，所以我们不仅有权使用
that waves and particles are the same
thing so we're entitled to use not only
我们通常认为是方式的事物，但我们通常认为是粒子的事物
things we usually think of as ways but
things we usually think of as particles
所以一个粒子很方便地进行散射实验
so a particle which is very convenient
to do scattering experiments with
你知道中子我认为中子是粒子，但是它们也在挥动
neutrons neutrons you know I think of as
in particles but they're also waves it
事实证明，获得中子的波长非常容易
turns out to be fairly easy to get
neutrons to have wavelengths which are
大约等于埃
on about the same scale of about an
angstrom
这样就很容易看到大约一埃的东西
which makes it easy to see things which
are on the scale of roughly an angstrom
这些几乎是我们要负责的两种类型的波浪
these are pretty much the two types of
waves that we're going to be responsible
今年，我应该提到人们经常使用电子波作为
for this year I should mention that
people frequently use electron waves as
好吧，但我们今年不研究它们，因为它们有一些并发症
well but we don't study them this year
because they have some complications
您不想钻研，所以无论我们发送到我们的任何类型的电波
which you don't want to delve into so
whatever type of wave we send into our
物质我们应该想象的是样品中的原子
material the thing that we're supposed
to imagine is that the atoms in sample
样品中的原子提供的电位V为R，它会散射它
atoms in the sample provide a potential
a potential V of R it scatters it
散射波散射波，我们的目标实际上是
scatters wave scatters the wave and our
objective is actually a bit of an
反问题，而不是试图计算潜在的潜力
inverse problem where instead of trying
to calculate what does the the potential
由于波浪的发生频率更高，我们被告知波浪已经完成了什么
due to the wave much more frequently
we're told what the wave has done we've
测量了波浪的作用，我们正在尝试推断出潜在的
measured what the wave has done and
we're trying to deduce the potential the
势将告诉我们原子在材料中的位置，而我们
potential is going to tell us where the
atoms are in the material and we're
试图通过观察我们样本中的物质得出结论
trying to deduce that from observing
what physically came out of our sample
现在只是一个警告，很容易想到潜在的
now just a little bit of a caveat it's
easy to think about a potential for
中子和中子在它周围移动时感觉有些潜能
neutrons and neutrons moves around it
feels some potential as it moves around
现在考虑潜在的机会要少一些
it's a little bit less now
to think about a potential for for
X射线是电磁波，如果需要，您可以
x-rays which are electromagnetic waves
you can if you want you can kind of
认为它有光子的潜力，但如果您真的
think of it as a potential for photons
but much more appropriate if you really
应该将其视为空间相关的光学指数或空间上的
should be thinking of it as spatially
dependent optical index or spatially
依赖于介电常数，但考虑到它不会太错误
dependent dielectric constant but you
won't go too far wrong to think about it
就像粒子在您的材料中移动时的潜在潜力一样
as just a potential for particles as a
particle move through your material so
我们实际上会撒尿的方式我们实际上会计算出多少
the way we're gonna actually scat and
we're gonna actually calculate how much
散布在某个波矢K素上是使用费米黄金定律
gets scattered out at some wave vector K
prime is to use Fermi's Golden Rule
费米的黄金法则浓缩的笑话你知道这是一个象征
Fermi's golden rule rule condensed
matter joke you know this is a symbol
还是因为他们的钱是黄金，所以我当场弥补了这是因为我当时
for gold anyway their money so I made
that up on the spot it was because I was
试图挽救我的手臂，以免写错了，没关系，我不会成为一个
trying to save my arm from writing all
right never mind I'm not gonna be a
喜剧演员这就是为什么我是物理学家，所以散射率散射率
comedian that's why I'm a physicist okay
so the scattering rate scattering rate
从K到K素数的振铃速率是由您给定的，您可能会看到费米的
ring rate from K to K prime is given by
you'll probably probably seen Fermi's
黄金法则h上的两个pi有一个矩阵元素K素数K
golden rule two pi over h-bar there's a
matrix element K prime the K that gets
平方和一个能量守恒Delta函数能量守恒Delta
squared and an energy preserving Delta
function energy preserving Delta
现在可以简化您的生活，我们假设我们假设有弹性
function now to simplify your life
we are going to assume we assume elastic
散射弹性散射，这意味着e等于E成为能量的主要来源
scattering elastic scatter which means
that e equals E prime the energy coming
进入和流出的能量是相同的，这也意味着绝对
in and the energy coming out are the
same that will also mean the absolute
K的值等于K素数的绝对值
value of K equals the absolute value of
K prime there's several reasons why we
首先假设弹性散射，然后当您实际
assume elastic scattering first of all
it's easier secondly when you actually
做这些实验你实际测量的大部分散射是
do these experiments most of the
scattering that you measure actually is
弹性，我对观察非弹性散射也很有趣
elastic is I did quite interesting to
look at inelastic scattering as well I
可能会提到一些关于非弹性散射的讲座
might mention that a couple of lectures
further on with the inelastic scattering
实际上，您会在样本中留下一些能量，而实际上
you actually get you leave some energy
behind in the sample and that actually
让您找出可能激发的能量是什么
allows you to figure out what the energy
of the possible excitations are that you
也可以使声音兴奋，但要多一点
can excite in the sound
as well but that's a little bit more
复杂，所以我们暂时不用担心，所以我们只是去
complicated so we're not gonna worry
about that for now so we're just going
假设弹性散射，唯一困难的是
to assume elastic scattering and the
only thing that's difficult in that
费米的黄金法则是矩阵元素，所以让我们写出
expression Fermi's golden rule is the
matrix elements so let's write out the
矩阵元素，所以我们有K个素数VK等于我们将使用实数
matrix element so we have K prime V K
equals what well we'll use the the real
这些猫的空间表示形式是e到罪恶e到e的积分
space representation of these cats it's
integral d dr of e to the sines e to the
r乘以e到i k点的ik质点rv是正确的标志，是的，
i k prime dot r v of r times e to the i
k dot are the signs right yeah okay and
如果您小心的话，我们会用1的平方根
if you were careful we would normalize
this with by 1 over square roots of
体积这是波向量这是波函数k素数这是
volumes this is a wave vector this is
the wave function k prime this is the
波动函数K在中间有R的V，我们意识到那是什么
wave function K there's V of R in the
middle and we realize that what that is
很好地这样写d 3r e到负IK素数减K
is well write this way d 3r e to the
minus I K prime minus K dotted with our
R的V就是将其写为K减去K素数K减去V的旋转
V of R that is just what will write it
as V twiddle of K minus K prime K minus
V旋转为K的素数表示傅里叶变换等于傅立叶
K prime where V twiddle is means Fourier
transform be twiddle equals Fourier
R的V的变换这是一个非常普遍的规则，即散射
transform of V of R this is a very very
general rule that the scattering
从K到K素数的振幅只是散射的傅立叶变换
amplitude from K to K prime is just the
Fourier transform of the scattering
现在在上一堂课中具有潜力，因此这几乎总是
potential now in the last lecture and so
this that actually always almost always
对于您将要进行散射实验的任何事情都适用
holds true for anything that you're
going to do scattering experiments on
使用形式的散射是黄金法则
that the scattering using form is Golden
Rule the scattering amplitude from some
K到K素数只是傅里叶变换或任何散射
K to K prime is just the Fourier
transform or whatever the scattering
潜力现在在上一讲中我们考虑了傅立叶变换
potential is now in the last lecture we
considered Fourier transforms of
周期函数，所以我们假设我们有一个晶体，让我们假设
periodic functions so we're going to
assume we have a crystal let's assume a
R的周期性周期性散射势V因此，如果我们有
periodic periodic scattering potential V
of R so if we have anything that's
结晶的潜力将是周期性的，因此我们可以使用以下定律
crystalline the potential will be
periodic and so we can use the law that
我们在上一讲中导出了周期的傅立叶变换
we derived in the last lecture if the
Fourier transform of a periodic
势K减去K素数等于
potential K minus K prime equals
等于三角函数3的倒数晶格向量G的和
equals sum over a reciprocal lattice
vectors G of a delta function three
K减去K素数的维度Delta函数K减去K素数减G
dimensional Delta function of K minus K
prime again K minus K prime minus G
乘以GI的结构因子猜测有一些归一化因子2 PI
times the structure factor of G I guess
there's some normalization factor 2 PI
求单位晶格体积本身的体积和结构因子的立方
cubed over the volume of the unit cell
volume itself and the structure factor
这里的走出空间s的g等于积分，等于
here s of g o running out of space s of
g equals the integral it's equal to the
知道单位晶格积分d3内的傅立叶变换
Fourier transform within a unit cell
integral d3 are you know I I do dot R of
R的V写入R的方式相同，并且在单位晶格上积分a
V of R write the R is the same way and
it's integral over the unit cell ok a
这很重要，所以这是我们上次推导的法律
couple of important so this is a law
that we derived last time and a couple
关于这条法律的重要事实，我们上次首先提到
of important facts about this this law
we mentioned last time first of all the
除非我们查看，否则该周期函数的傅立叶变换为零
Fourier transform of this periodic
function is zero unless we're looking at
K的值是倒数晶格向量的元素，所以0.1
values of K which are elements of the
reciprocal lattice vector so 0.1
除非0减去K素数是倒数晶格，否则散射为0为0
scattering is 0 is 0 unless unless K
minus K prime is a reciprocal lattice
向量G这是一个重要的框，称为低e条件
vector G this is important box around it
this is known as the low e condition
继马克·冯·劳埃二世（Max von Laue II）之后，他因在X射线中发现这一点而获得了诺贝尔奖
after Max von Laue II who won a Nobel
Prize for discovering this in x-ray
散布的诺贝尔奖实际上不时是一百年前
scattering Nobel Prize was actually
exactly a hundred years ago now and then
关于是否应将其称为“糟糕的条件”存在复杂性
there's this complication about whether
it should be called a lousy condition of
冯·劳厄（von Laue e）的病情，因为他出生于麦克斯洛（maxchloe），但后来他的父亲
the von Laue e condition because he was
born maxchloe but then his father was
后来升为贵族，他取了冯·劳埃二世的名字，但是当他
elevated to noble hood much later and he
took the name von Laue ii but when he
发现他的名字仍然是低e，所以通常称为低e
discovered this his name was still low e
so it's usually called the low e
关于条件元音的条件，但其他人会
condition about the vowel i of
conditions but other people will
因此不同意，无论是von laue e条件的响亮状态，还是
disagree so anyway it's either loud
condition of von laue e condition and
但是我们在这是什么之前就已经看过了
but we've seen this thing before what
this is
是守恒的晶体动量守恒
is conservation of conservation of
crystal momentum
只有在您可以保留晶体动量的情况下，才散布
you only scatter if you can conserve
crystal momentum right K if K minus K
质数是互易的晶格矢量，可保持其晶体动量
prime is a reciprocal lattice vector
that conserves crystal momentum it
第二个重要事实是不会改变波浪的晶体动量
doesn't change the crystal momentum of
the wave the second important fact that
我们稍后将使用的是
we're going to use later is that the
intensity of scattering intensity of
我的散射是井Delta Delta K平方的结构因子s
scattering I'm scatter is the structure
factor s of well Delta Delta K squared
这里的Delta K是你已经分散的倒数晶格矢量G
where Delta K is the reciprocal lattice
vector G which you've scattered by okay
所以重点是，如果您测量各种散射的强度
so the point is that if you measure the
intensity of the various scatterings
您可以弄清楚要测量的结构因素是
you can figure out the structure factor
you what you're measuring is the
给定倒数晶格矢量的结构因子
structure factor at given reciprocal
lattice vectors the structure factor of
鉴于您在晶格因子处的典型R是
given your typical R at lattice factors
is the Fourier transform of the
散射势，所以原则上您正在测量散射
scattering potential so in principle
you're measuring the scattering
通过测量所散布的点来确定潜力
potential that's the point
by measuring the what is scattered
您实际上正在测量散射潜力，对不起，我要去了
you're actually measuring the scattering
potential now I'm sorry I'm going to go
在大约一分钟的时间里，这种情况似乎有些令人惊讶
over about one minute here it may seem a
little bit surprising this condition one
你只会在特定条件下散布
that you only get scattering under
certain conditions
只有满足了水晶的动量才满足
only if crystal momentum is satisfied
only if you if satisfy this lousy
现在看起来有些奇怪，但我要说服你
condition now that might seem a little
bit weird but I'm going to convince you
这是你非常了解的东西，所以想象你有一个水晶
that this is something that you know
very well so imagine you have a crystal
像这样，那么你想到的是，这确实是一堆晶格平面
like this then you think of there's a
really this is a bunch of lattice planes
这是一个晶格平面族，您将一些波发送到一个晶格家族中
it's a family of lattice planes and you
send some wave into a family of lattice
飞机，它会弹起，但它也可能从这一层弹起，你知道
planes and it bounces off but it could
bounce off this layer too and you know
很好，如果您像这样从平面上弹开，您会得到衍射和
very well that if you bounce off planes
like this you can get diffraction and
衍射仅在特定角度发生
diffraction only occurs at certain
angles
您只会在某些角度获得建设性的干涉
you only get constructive interference
at certain angles and what we're going
看到的是，这种糟糕的情况实际上与
to see is that this lousy condition is
actually exactly the same condition as
有建设性的干涉，我们下次见到您时会做
having constructive interference and
we'll do that next time I see you
星期三[掌声]
Wednesday
[Applause]